Guide to the Champion Spalding Chase Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Champion Spalding Chase papers
1837-1899
MS 133
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
7
(16 boxes)
Correspondence and other papers of Champion Spalding Chase, Civil War veteran, lawyer, and politician. The papers are comprised primarily of personal correspondence between Chase and members of the family, although there is some material related to his Civil War experiences and to his work with the Whig Party and the Republican Party.
Chase, Champion Spalding, 1820-1898
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Sherret Chase, 1966.
Arrangement
Arranged in two series: I. Correspondence. II. Special Files.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Scope and Contents
The Champion Spalding Chase Papers comprise a total of 16 boxes of papers and are divided into two series: CORRESPONDENCE, which makes up the bulk of the papers, and a small SPECIAL FILES series. CORRESPONDENCE is divided into three subsections: "Correspondence of C.S. Chase", "Correspondence of M.S. Chase," his wife, and "Correspondence of Others." The first two subsections comprise the bulk of the Correspondence and consist primarily of letters exchanged between Chase and his wife. This correspondence covers the years 1845-1881, with a particularly large number of letters from 1863 to 1864. Although these letters are mostly of a personal nature, there is some discussion of Civil War matters, including a description of the surrender of Vicksburg. Also included in the "Correspondence of C.S. Chase" is a small number of letters from J.R. Doolittle, William H. Seward, and Fitz H. Warren, discussing the Whig Party's attempt to elect General Winfield Scott to the Presidency in 1852. There is, however, very little correspondence covering the years during which Chase was mayor of Omaha.
SPECIAL FILES contains a variety of items, the most important of which are Chase's military appointments and orders. Also included is a genealogy of the Chase family printed in 1894.
Biographical / Historical
Champion Spalding Chase was born March 20, 1820, in Cornish, New Hampshire, the son of Clement and Olive (Spalding) Chase. He studied law in Buffalo, New York, and was admitted to the New York Bar in 1847. In that year, Chase moved to the Territory of Wisconsin. He married Mary Sophrina Butterfield, daughter of a prominent lawyer, in 1848, and in the same year opened a law office in Racine, where he remained until entering the Union Army in 1862. Chase also gave public lectures on phrenology and mesmerism.
Chase held a variety of public offices in the ante-bellum years. He served on the Board of Education of Racine from 1853-1857, including two years as president. In 1856, following the breakup of the Whig Party, which he had supported, Chase served as a delegate to the first National Republican Convention in Philadelphia. The same year, he was elected to a two-year term in the Wisconsin State Senate, where he spoke against the further extension of slavery. In 1859, Chase was appointed District Attorney of the First Judicial District.
In 1862, at the recommendation of his cousin, Salmon P. Chase, he was commissioned paymaster in the Union Army with the rank of major. Chase served in the army nearly four years, spending much of that time in the west and south-west. He witnessed the sieges of Knoxville, Mobile, and Vicksburg and for more than two years was stationed in New Orleans. Owing in part, at least, to the influence of William H. Seward, Chase was breveted Lieutenant Colonel by President Andrew Johnson. In January of 1866, he was honorably discharged and in the same year he moved to Omaha in the Territory of Nebraska. The following year, he became the first Attorney General of the new State of Nebraska.
In 1874, Chase was elected mayor of Omaha. He was re-elected in 1875, 1879, and 1883, serving a total of seven years in that office.
During his later years, Chase spent much of his time acting as delegate to various conventions called to consider current public issues. He died about 1898.
Families; Law; Popular culture; Middle West; Nebraska -- Politics and government; United States -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865; United States -- Politics and government; West (U.S.); Wisconsin -- Politics and government; Lawyers; Politicians; Chase, Champion Spalding, 1820-1898; Doolittle, James R. (James Rood), 1815-1897; Seward, William H. (William Henry), 1801-1872; Warren, Fitz Henry, 1816-1878; Republican Party (U.S.: 1854- ); Whig Party (U.S.)
- Correspondence, 1837, 1840-1842 1844-1859, 1861-(1863-1864)-1871, 1874-1875, 1877-1881, 1899; Series I; 6'3" - 15 boxes
  Scope and Contents
  CORRESPONDENCE contains three subsections. The first, "Correspondence of C.S. Chase", is divided into a large group of letters received by Chase, primarily from his wife, and a small group of letters written by Chase to others (except his wife). Letters received by Chase are arranged alphabetically by the name of the writer and chronologically within each folder. Letters written by Chase are arranged alphabetically by the name of the person to whom they are addressed.
  The second subsection, "Correspondence of M.S. Chase", is divided between a large group of letters received by M.S. Chase, primarily from her husband, followed by a small group of letters written by M.S. Chase to others (except her husband). Letters received by M.S. Chase are arranged alphabetically by the name of the writer and chronologically within each folder; letters written by M.S. Chase are arranged alphabetically by the name of the person to whom they are addressed.
  The third subsection, "Correspondence of Others", is arranged alphabetically by the name of the writer. It consists primarily of Butterfield family correspondence and also includes several letters endorsing C.S. Chase for various military and political positions.
  - Correspondence of Champion Spalding Chase From:
    - A, 1865 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Be - Bus, 1863, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Butterfield, Elizabeth, 1858-1866 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Butterfield, Emily, 1858-1866, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Butterfield, M.B. and M.D., 1843-1865 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Butterfield, Mellie, 1880 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - C (except Chase, George and Chase, M. S.), 1843-1867, 1879, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Chase, George M., 1849-1864 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Chase, Mary S.
      - 1845, Jul 13 - Nov 10 (Box 1, Folder 9)
      - 1846, Jan 4 - Sep 19, Oct 4 - Dec 21 (Box 1, Folder 10-11)
      - 1847, Jan 3 - Feb 8, Feb 27 - Jun 3, Jul 13 - Aug 11, Aug 20 - Sep 18, Sep 27 - Dec 8, Dec 11 - Dec 31 (Box 1, Folder 12-17)
      - 1848, Jan 3 - Jan 30 (Box 1, Folder 18)
      - 1848, Jan 3 - Jan 30, Feb 2 - Feb 18, Mar 6 - Apr 1, Dec 18 - Dec 29 (Box 2, Folder 19-21)
      - 1849, Jan 10 - Jan 30, Feb 22 - Feb 28, Mar 3 - Mar 20, Mar 22 - Apr 2, Apr 11 - Oct 6 (Box 2, Folder 22-26)
      - 1850, Feb 18 - Feb 29, Dec 21 - Dec 30 (Box 2, Folder 27-28)
      - 1851, Jan 2 - Jan 14, Jan 18 - Jan 31, Feb 5 - Feb 20, Mar 3 - Mar 26, May 14 - Dec 21 (Box 2, Folder 29-33)
      - 1852, May 11 - May 25 (Box 2, Folder 34)
      - 1857, Jan 12 - Jan 28, Feb 2 - Mar 7 (Box 2, Folder 35-36)
      - 1858, Jan 11 - Mar 17 (Box 2, Folder 37-40)
      - 1858, Mar 18 - Mar 29, Apr 9 - Apr 19, May 5 - May 12 (Box 3, Folder 41-43)
      - 1861, Mar 19 - Mar 29, Apr 1 - Jul 2, Jul 14 - Jul 31 (Box 3, Folder 44-46)
      - 1863, Jan 1 - Feb 10, Feb 12 - Feb 27, Mar 1 - Mar 29, Apr 2 - May 7, Jun 2 - Jun 26, Jul 1 - Jul 30, Sep 8 - Sep 20, Sep 22 - Oct 4, Oct 6 - Oct 30, Nov 1 - Nov 12, Nov 15 - Nov 26, Dec 2 - Dec 13, Dec 15 - Dec 30 (Box 3, Folder 47-64)
      - 1864, Jan 8 - Feb 27, Mar 5 - Mar 14, Mar 16 - Mar 31, Apr 3 - Apr 21, May 9 - May 16, May 19 - May 31, Jun 2 - Jun 15, Jun 17 - Jun 30, Jul 3 - Jul 15, Jul 17 - Jul 31, Aug 3 - Aug 14, Aug 16 - Aug 29, Sep 1 - Sep 15, Sep 18 - Sep 29, Oct 2 - Nov 2 (Box 4, Folder 65-83)
      - 1865, Aug 27 - Sep 26 (Box 4, Folder 84)
      - 1866, Sep 23 - Dec 30 (Box 5, Folder 85)
      - 1867, Jan 2 -Jan 13, Jan 15 - Jan 31, Feb 2 - Feb 19, Mar 5 - Mar 16, Mar 19 - Mar 31, Apr 1 - Apr 14, Apr 16 - Apr 28, May 1 - May 14 (Box 5, Folder 86-93)
      - 1869, Feb 4 - Feb 7 (Box 5, Folder 94)
      - no year, no date (Box 5, Folder 95-96)
    - D (except Doolittle), 1863, 1867 (Box 5, Folder 97)
    - Doolittle, James R., 1861 (Box 5, Folder 98)
    - E, 1866 (Box 5, Folder 99)
    - F (except Fillmore), 1865, 1878, 1883, undated (Box 5, Folder 100)
    - Fillmore, M. P., 1851-1852 (Box 5, Folder 101)
    - G, 1863 (Box 5, Folder 102)
    - H, 1861-1864, undated (Box 5, Folder 103)
    - J, 1853, 1863-1867, 1873, undated (Box 5, Folder 104)
    - K, 1852, 1863 (Box 5, Folder 105)
    - L, 1848-1853, 1863-1866 (Box 5, Folder 106)
    - M, 1850, 1857, 1863, 1864 (Box 5, Folder 107)
    - N, 1859, 1863, 1865 (Box 5, Folder 108)
    - P, 1865 (Box 5, Folder 109)
    - R, 1863 (Box 5, Folder 110)
    - S (except Seward), 1851, 1853, 1863, 1865, 1880, undated (Box 6, Folder 111)
    - Seward, William H., 1852, 1866, undated (Box 6, Folder 112)
    - T, 1863-1865 (Box 6, Folder 113)
    - W (except Warren), 1852, undated (Box 6, Folder 114)
    - Warren, Fitz H., 1852 (Box 6, Folder 115)
    - First Name Only, 1849, 1863 (Box 6, Folder 116)
    - Unidentified, 1863, undated (Box 6, Folder 117)
  - Correspondence of Champion Spalding Chase To:
    - B, 1849, 1865 (Box 6, Folder 118)
    - Chase, C. Clement (son), 1863-1865, 1870-1871, 1875, undated (Box 6, Folder 119)
    - Chase, Clement (father), 1863 (Box 6, Folder 120)
    - G, 1863 (Box 6, Folder 121)
    - P, 1866 (Box 6, Folder 122)
    - S, 1866 (Box 6, Folder 123)
    - First Name Only, 1863 (Box 6, Folder 124)
    - Unidentified, 1849, 1861, 1865 (Box 6, Folder 125)
  - Correspondence of Mary S. Chase From: (re Anniversary and Silver Wedding)
    - A-B, 1873 (Box 6, Folder 126)
    - C - E, 1873 (Box 6, Folder 127)
    - F - M, 1873 (Box 6, Folder 128)
    - P - Y, 1873 (Box 6, Folder 129)
  - Correspondence of Mary S. Chase From:
    - B (except Butterfield), 1836, 1845, 1848, 1852, 1853, 1863, 1875-1877, 1880, undated (Box 6, Folder 130)
    - Butterfield, Elizabeth, 1847, 1849, 1863-1864 (Box 7, Folder 131)
    - Butterfield, Emily, 1847, 1849 (Box 7, Folder 132)
    - Butterfield, M.B. and M.D.
      - 1837, Jan 6 - Apr 10 (Box 7, Folder 133)
      - 1840, Aug 24 - Nov 29 (Box 7, Folder 134)
      - 1841-1842 (Box 7, Folder 135)
      - 1844, Jan 29 - Aug 19, Sep 3 - Nov 24, Nov 29 - Dec 29 (Box 7, Folder 136-138)
      - 1845, Jan 21 - Mar 23, Apr 6 - Apr 27, May 11 - Jun 22, Jul 10 - Aug 1 (Box 7, Folder 139-142)
      - 1847, May 3 - Dec 10 (Box 7, Folder 143)
      - 1848, Jan 20 - Mar 16 (Box 7, Folder 144)
      - 1849, May 31 - Jun 23 (Box 7, Folder 145)
      - 1858, Nov 8 (Box 7, Folder 146)
      - undated (Box 7, Folder 147)
    - Butterfield, Mellie, 1880 (Box 7, Folder 148)
    - C (except Chase), 1846, 1875, undated (Box 7, Folder 149)
    - Chase, C. S.
      - 1845, Jun 17 - Dec 15 (Box 7, Folder 150)
      - 1846, Jan 26 - Aug 15, Aug 24 - Nov 2 (Box 7, Folder 151-152)
      - 1846, Nov 11 - Dec 29 (Box 8, Folder 158)
      - 1847, Jan 16 - Feb 25, Mar 8 - Apr 28, May 8 - June 17, Jul 1 - Aug 6, Aug 13 - Aug 30, Sep 5 - Sep 25, Oct 2 - Oct 28, Dec 9 - Dec 14, Dec 16 - Dec 31 (Box 8, Folder 154-162)
      - 1848, Jan 1 - Jan 18, Jan 19 - Jan 30, Feb 2 - Feb 15, Mar 17 - Mar 21, Mar 23 - Mar 28, Dec 18 - Dec 27 (Box 8, Folder 163-168)
      - 1849, Jan 9 - Jan 30, Feb 21 - Feb 27, Mar 1 - Mar 11, Mar 14 - Mar 30, Apr 8 - Nov 12 (Box 8, Folder 169-173)
      - 1850, Jan 1 -Jan 30, Feb 1 - Feb 28 (Box 8, Folder 174-175)
      - 1850, Apr 8 - Dec 27 (Box 9, Folder 176)
      - 1851, Jan 5 - Jan 18, Jan 22 - Jan 28, Feb 2 - Feb 11, Feb 12 - Feb 28, Mar 2 - Mar 15, Mar 17 - Mar 28, Apr 1 - Apr 7, May 10 - May 18, May 21 - May 31, Sep 22 - Dec 29 (Box 9, Folder 177-186)
      - 1852, Oct 29 (Box 9, Folder 187)
      - 1853, Jan 19 - Jul 12 (Box 9, Folder 188)
      - 1854, Feb 15 (Box 9, Folder 189)
      - 1855, Mar 30 (Box 9, Folder 190)
      - 1856, Jan 2 - Jan 22 (Box 9, Folder 191)
      - 1857, Jan 1 - Jan 24, Jan 25 - Jan 29, Feb 2 - Sep 1 (Box 9, Folder 192-194)
      - 1858, Jan 12 - Jan 16, Jan 17 - Jan 30, Feb 1 - Feb 12, Feb 14 - Feb 28, Mar 1 - Mar 14, Mar 15 - Mar 28 (Box 9, Folder 195-200)
      - 1858, Apr 9 - Apr 20, May 4 - May 16 (Box 10, Folder 201-202)
      - 1859, Feb 7 - Feb 9 (Box 10, Folder 203)
      - 1861, Mar 18 - Mar 31, Apr 2 - Apr 14, Jun 11 - Jun 15, Jun 23 - Jun 27, Jul 1 - Jul 18, Jul 20 - Aug 14 (Box 10, Folder 204-209)
      - 1862, Jan 28 - Dec 31 (Box 10, Folder 210)
      - 1863, Jan 1 - Jan 18, Jan 19 - Jan 23, Jan 24 - Jan 30, Feb 1 - Feb 9, Feb 12 - Feb 27, Mar 1 - Mar 9, Mar 11 - Mar 18, Mar 19 - Mar 31, Apr 2 - Apr 19 (Box 10, Folder 211-220)
      - 1863, Apr 20 - Apr 29, May 1 - May 7, Jun 3 - Jun 8, Jun 11 - Jun 27, Jul 4 - Jul 31, Aug 2 - Sep 29, Oct 2 - Oct 19, Oct 21 - Oct 30, Nov 3 - Nov 10, Nov 12 - Nov 22, Dec 1 - Dec 15, Dec 16 - Dec 19, Dec 20 - Dec 26 (Box 11, Folder 221-233)
      - 1864, Jan 7 - Jan 18, Jan 20 - Jan 30, Feb 1 - Feb 15, Feb 16 - Feb 26, Mar 5 - Mar 31, Apr 3 - Apr 20 (Box 11, Folder 234-239)
      - 1864, May 10 - May 16, May 18 - Jul 8, Jul 10 - Jul 31, Aug 3 - Aug 13, Aug 17 - Aug 30, Sep 2 - Sep 10, Sep 15 - Sep 29, Oct 2 - Oct 16, Oct 20 - Nov 5 (Box 12, Folder 240-253)
      - 1865, Jul 25 - Aug 30, Sep 1 - Sep 14 (Box 12, Folder 254-255)
      - 1865, Sep 19 - Sep 25 (Box 13, Folder 256)
      - 1866, Jan 3 - Dec 31 (Box 13, Folder 257-258)
      - 1867, Jan 4 - Jan 31, Feb 4 - Feb 17, Mar 5 - Mar 31, Apr 2 - Apr 15, Apr 18 - Apr 30, May 1 - May 10 (Box 13, Folder 259-266)
      - 1868, Mar 3 - Mar 5 (Box 13, Folder 267)
      - 1869, Feb 4 - Sep 21 (Box 13, Folder 268)
      - 1870, Jul 4 - Dec 23 (Box 13, Folder 269)
      - 1871, Jan 5 - Jan 13, Jan 15 - Feb 25, Mar 2 - Sep 24 (Box 13, Folder 270-272)
      - 1874, Apr 13 (Box 13, Folder 273)
      - 1875, Aug 12 - Aug 20 (Box 13, Folder 274)
      - 1875, Aug 21 - Sep 12, Sep 14 - Sep 29 (Box 14, Folder 275-277)
      - 1877, Oct 24 - Nov 17 (Box 14, Folder 278)
      - 1878, Jun 9 - Sep 25 (Box 14, Folder 279)
      - 1879, Jan 13 - Jun 10 (Box 14, Folder 280)
      - 1880, Nov 13 (Box 14, Folder 281)
      - 1881, Nov 29 - Nov 30 (Box 14, Folder 282)
      - no year (Box 14, Folder 283-284)
      - no date (Box 14, Folder 285-286)
    - E, 1873 (Box 14, Folder 287)
    - F, 1861, 1863 (Box 14, Folder 288)
    - G, 1853 (Box 14, Folder 289)
    - H, 1845, 1876-1877, 1880-1881 (Box 14, Folder 290)
    - J, 1845, 1864, 1878, 1880-1881 (Box 14, Folder 291)
    - K, 1846 (Box 14, Folder 292)
    - L, 1844 (Box 14, Folder 293)
    - M, 1843, 1845-1847, 1875-1880 (Box 14, Folder 294)
    - P, undated (Box 14, Folder 295)
    - R, 1845-1846 (Box 14, Folder 296)
    - S, 1845, 1847, 1851, 1878-1881, undated (Box 14, Folder 297)
    - T, undated (Box 14, Folder 298)
    - W, 1879 (Box 14, Folder 299)
    - First Name Only, A - H, 1843, 1845-1846, 1851, 1853, undated (Box 14, Folder 300)
    - First Name Only, J - L, 1843, 1845-1847, undated (Box 14, Folder 301)
    - First Name Only, M, 1846-1847, undated (Box 15, Folder 302)
    - First Name Only, N - Z, 1845-1846, undated (Box 15, Folder 303)
    - Unidentified, 1845, 1880, undated (Box 15, Folder 304)
  - To:
    - Butterfield, M.B. and M.D., 1838-1851 (Box 15, Folder 305-306)
    - Butterfield, M.B. and M.D., undated (Box 15, Folder 307)
    - G- S, 1845, undated (Box 15, Folder 308)
    - Unidentified, 1881, undated (Box 15, Folder 309)
  - Correspondence of Others From:
    - A, 1861, 1899 (Box 15, Folder 310)
    - Burr, 1844-1845, 1847 (Box 15, Folder 311)
    - Butterfield, E. and M.B., 1842, 1845, 1854, 1854, 1871 (Box 15, Folder 312)
    - Butterfield, M.D., 1842, 1845, 1849, 1852, 1853, undated (Box 15, Folder 313)
    - C (except Canby), 1845, 1847, 1861-1863, 1867 (Box 15, Folder 314)
    - Canby, 1866 (Box 15, Folder 315)
    - D, 1844, 1861, 1863 (Box 15, Folder 316)
    - G, 1845 (Box 15, Folder 317)
    - M, 1843, 1845, 1863 (Box 15, Folder 318)
    - N, 1854, 1861, undated (Box 15, Folder 319)
    - P, 1864 (Box 15, Folder 320)
    - S, 1844 (Box 15, Folder 321)
    - T, 1850 (Box 15, Folder 322)
    - W, 1836 (Box 15, Folder 323)
    - Y, 1845 (Box 15, Folder 324)
    - Unidentified Fragments, undated (Box 15, Folder 325)
- Special Files, 1843-1894; Series II; 0.25; (1 box)
  SPECIAL FILES are arranged alphabetically by category or subject.
  - Advertisements and Announcements, 1848, 1857, 1863, undated (Box 16, Folder 1)
  - Bills and Documents: Butterfield, 1821, 1845 (Box 16, Folder 2)
  - Bills and Receipts: Chase, C. S., 1849, 1860, 1864, undated (Box 16, Folder 3)
  - Cards: Business, 1863, undated (Box 16, Folder 4)
  - Cards: New Year's, 1872, 1879 (Box 16, Folder 5)
  - Cards: Visiting, undated (Box 16, Folder 6)
  - Floor Plans, undated (Box 16, Folder 7)
  - Genealogy, 1894 (Box 16, Folder 8)
  - Invitations, 1848, 1865, 1868, 1873, undated (Box 16, Folder 9)
  - Menus, 1848, 1851 1861 1863, 1867 (Box 16, Folder 10)
  - Military: Appointments and Orders, 1862-1866 (Box 16, Folder 11)
  - Military: Financial Papers, 1863-1867 (Box 16, Folder 12)
  - Military: Passes, 1863-1866 (Box 16, Folder 13)
  - Notes and Writings: C. S. Chase, 1843, undated (Box 16, Folder 14)
  - Notes and Writings: M. S. Chase, 1846, undated (Box 16, Folder 15)
  - Photos and Drawings, undated (Box 16, Folder 16)
  - Printed Matter, 1882, 1889, 1893, undated (Box 16, Folder 17)
  - Railroad Passes, 1856, 1866-1868 (Box 16, Folder 18)
  - Souvenirs, 1845, 1865, 1866, 1880, undated (Box 16, Folder 19)